[Music]
[Applause]
should i train to failure
take one
what's up everybody welcome back to the
channel for those of you who are new to
the channel or those of you who don't
know me my name is brett cantress aka
the glute guy i've been lifting for 30
years training people for 25 years i got
my first cpt certification 25 years ago
i got my first cscs certification from
the nsa that's a certified strength and
conditioning specialist 23 years ago i
own a gym in san diego called glute lab
i'm the inventor of the barbell hip
thrust i have a phd in sports science my
thesis was pretty much on glutes i
trained some freakishly strong women out
of my glute lab in san diego they're
known as the glute squad i'm the founder
of booty by brett bc strength bc academy
the strength sport of strong lifting i'm
the creator of this whole glute niche
i've invented many exercises and pieces
of equipment and in general you'll never
meet somebody more enthusiastic about
lifting weights and strength training
than me i live it breathe it bleed it
sleep it that's all i think about i'm
single i don't have any kids and i'm
constantly bombarded with strength and
conditioning stuff around the clock i'm
either working out training people
reading research writing programs
creating content or working on new
projects now that you know a little bit
about me let's dive right in to train to
failure or not to train to failure that
is the question that i want to tackle
today so first let me discuss the theory
and some history behind training to
failure so i grew up reading
bodybuilding magazines and i remember a
lot of the bodybuilders you know i'd
read their columns and they'd be like i
take every single set to failure but
then they'd be saying something like you
know with with like pull-ups they do 15
reps and then 15 reps and then 15 reps
all to failure well you can't do three
sets of 15 reps that would mean you're
really not going to failure because if
you really want to failure on pull-ups
you never see 15 15 15 on something like
pull-ups what you'd normally see is
maybe like 15 12 7 or something like
that that's the way it goes when you
really go to true failure so looking
back they all just lied about going to
failure on every set because they wanted
to appear more hardcore now as soon as
the internet became popular you know
like like late 90s i stumbled upon a
couple different websites one was called
hardgainer and the other was called
cyberpump and they were all about one
set to failure i remember reading it
going like what why would you just do
one set that sounds silly you know if if
you look up you know arthur jones he was
the inventor of nautilus he espoused
this one set to failure you know you do
like say you know 12 different machines
you do one set to failure on each
machine for 12 total sets and that was
your workout and the further i dove into
this the more legit it sounded okay you
know first of all uh with hit training
or like hit training not to be confused
with
hit training like high intensity
interval training hit training hit just
one eye stood for high intensity
training which meant
just do one all-out set to fill you can
warm up do as many warm-up sets as you
like but you're only having one working
set and you go to all-out failure there
was an even more extreme spin-off called
heavy-duty training uh that was
championed by mike menser who was a very
popular bodybuilder but you know dorian
yates did hit training he won the mr
olympia he was all about one set to
failure so if you're a little bit older
like me and you've been reading strength
and conditioning material for you know
30 years then you have undoubtedly
stumbled across the colorado experiment
now the colorado experiment took place
in may of 1973 at colorado state
university it involved bodybuilder casey
viator it lasted 28 days long and it
involved 14 workouts so every other day
he did a workout now these workouts
involved one set to failure on between 8
to 14 exercises per training day at the
end of the 28 days casey supposedly put
on 63 pounds of muscle mass here you can
see a picture of the results so i
remember reading that going this is
silly it's a hoax you know you can't put
63 pounds of muscle on in 28 days but
there was a lot of hype about this type
of training and all the authors on those
websites back in the day you know this
is 20 years ago they were all very
compelling about the rationale behind
hit training and they'd say that in
order to spark continuous growth you had
to do more than you've ever done before
you know they would say the only thing
that grows muscle is beating prs setting
personal records the muscle has adapted
to what it's previously done the only
way to get it to further adapt is by
doing more so you have to do more over
time you have to beat pr's and in order
to do that you got to be pushing
yourself so hard that you know you do
one all-out set and you don't even want
to do another set and they would say if
you did want to do another set that's
just evidence that you didn't push
yourself hard enough so when i was 24
years old i started doing hit training
you know one set to failure and
ironically the eight months that i did
hit training was the best results i've
ever seen in my life i'm actually a big
champion of low volume high intensity
training before that i had been doing
eight straight years of high volume body
part split training just like the
bodybuilders do and i never deloaded you
know i was just always doing high volume
high volume high volume so it was
probably the change of pace that led to
my great results also during that time i
really learned how to push to failure
it's a skill that you build up over time
you get better at going to failure and
this is especially true on certain lower
body exercises for example squats lunges
deadlifts i recall back then the best
set i ever did at squats was with 225
but i did 30 reps now granted it took me
nine minutes but i kept that bar on my
back and you do what's called breathing
squats you know maybe i got the first 10
in a row without stopping and then you
stop and you breathe
get two more
get two more you know and then you just
keep it's just it's grueling to watch
it's painful but you get good at
buffering that lactic acid and you know
pushing through the pain and i remember
it was nine minutes i got 30 reps with
the squat and even more impressive me
and my buddy would kind of battle each
other each week i only had one pair of
dumbbells back then i had just started
building my garage gym i held on to a
pair of 25 pound dumbbells i still have
them to this day those same dumbbells
and i had a carport tent in the garage
and that's where i did my workouts you
know but me and my buddy larry we walked
out to the street and the first week i
did 50 lunges then the next week he did
70. the next week after that i got 80.
we kept one upping each other then he
ended up getting a hundred and i was
like man how am i gonna beat that well i
grabbed those dumbbells the following
week and i just kept walking
all the way down my street and all the
way back you know i remember i do 50 in
a row then i'd breathe for a while then
i do 10 more then 10 more the last few
minutes you're just doing one lunge at a
time i got 180 steps but i went all the
way down the street and all the way back
larry actually got 200 lunges he beat me
but he didn't beat me in distance
because i take longer strides than him
so at that point we decided to call a
truce i have never done a set of lunges
like that since and that was around 20
years ago during that set my forearms
would be screaming just from you know
try holding on to a pair of 25 pound
dumbbells for 11 straight minutes your
traps would be screaming your lungs
would be screaming your quads your
glutes your adductors that's about the
only time that i've ever done anything
for such ultra high reps and had it
actually transfer to my normal wraps
usually that style of training only
builds strength endurance but i worked
so hard on those that when i went back
to barbell walking lunges with more
weight i was actually stronger than
before so i do like hit training i think
it's a viable way of training i think
it's the most economical way of training
you know the first set is by far the
most important set you probably get 85
of your gains from that very first set
and to provide a more scientific
explanation for why it works then we
need to discuss what's known as the
henneman size principle and what this
means is that as you fatigue metabolic
byproducts you start interfering with
the contraction so you need to call upon
more and more motor units in order to
keep the set going right so that when
you go to actual failure you can't do
another rep at that point you're
recruiting all the motor units that you
can you know your nervous system is not
leaving any stones left unturned they're
recruiting everything you've got in
order to do that set and this henneman
size principle helps explain why in the
research low load training is equal to
high load training for building muscle
even though in the heavier loads right
away you're activating most of your
motor units with lighter loads you're
activating most of your motor units
towards the end of the set but because
the set is longer you end up cycling
through those motor units the end result
is around equal hypertrophy between
lower loads and high loads and a lot of
that can be explained by hannemann
science principle now henneman's size
prince was used to explain why you
should be training to failure the theory
sounds great right but as the legendary
physicist richard feyman says theory has
to match experiments if theory does not
match experiments no matter how eloquent
it is it's wrong
to see what if this is right if this law
that we guessed is right we see what it
would imply
and then we compare those computation
results
to nature
or we say compared to experiment or
experience
if it disagrees with experiment
[Applause]
it's wrong
in that simple statement
is the key to science it doesn't make a
difference how beautiful your guess is
it doesn't make you give it how smart
you are who made to get or what his name
is if it disagrees with experiment
it's wrong now during those last couple
reps where you're just grinding it out
squeezing squeezing you meet two
necessary conditions to maximize
mechanical tension you know owing to the
force velocity curve the ref speed has
to be slow enough to maximize force too
fast of a rep and you don't maximize
crossbridge formation you know the
sarcomeres can't do their thing so to
maximize tension on the muscle the rep
has to be slow and you need high motor
unit recruitment you know you have to
have high activation but because you're
so fatigued you are getting that high
activation even though you have lighter
loads you know so if you have a heavy
load say you're doing you know 95 or one
rep max for a double both reps will be
very slow and grindy whereas if you do
you know
30 percent of one rep max for 30 reps
the last few reps might be slow and
grindy but in both those scenarios you
will have high mechanical tension so
what happens in the research five years
ago there were only around 10 studies on
training to failure since then a lot
more studies have emerged but the
consensus is training the failure is not
mandatory to maximize hypertrophy
strength or power and depending on the
researcher and kind of depending on the
study you look at there is some evidence
that might suggest that training a
failure is worthwhile sometimes there's
also some evidence that shows that it's
detrimental sometimes for muscle
hypertrophy you definitely don't need to
take all your sets to failure for
strength it's even more apparent you
don't need to go to failure and for
power output if you're an athlete you
definitely should not train to failure
if you're an athlete you don't want
those slow grindy reps in the research
for athletes on power production we've
seen a lot of research emerge on cluster
training and on velocity-based training
but you can just think of olympic weight
lifters versus power lifters you know
power lifters are regularly grinding out
reps very slow force production whereas
olympic lifters are always snappy you
know you never see them really grinding
out their stuff they're always explosive
and they train more frequently than the
power lifters but they're always snappy
you know they keep their reps rather
quick and for that reason you tend to
see olympic weight lifters with these
crazy vertical jumps you know i've seen
power lifters too but in general power
lifters are slower than weight lifters
they're not as good at producing power
so if you're an athlete do not train to
failure don't perform any slow grindy
reps and look into cluster and
velocity-based training so we've
discussed theory we've discussed
research now let's talk about the
different types of failure okay most
training to failure you see people go
yeah i took that set to failure and
there's a researcher by the name of
steele james steele he says that's not
real failure training if you say you
went to phil you have to actually fail i
know this happens to me on a regular
basis especially with bench press i get
up to here oh i can't do it boom i need
my spotter to help me rack it or if i
didn't have a spotter hopefully i put
the safety pins at the proper height
where i can just roll it onto the safety
pins and duck out underneath it or worst
case scenario i don't have clips at the
end of the bar and i have to just like
squirm and move side to side until the
plates fall off i hate to recommend that
but it's a lot safer than having the
clips on the bar and having and being
pinned under the bar if you roll it
backwards
you will
suffocate yourself or like choke
yourself to death so you have to roll
the bar forwards and then it rolls over
your belly you'll get like bruised the
next day and then you have to sit up and
do this weird
stand-up deadlift type thing and throw
the bar on the floor it sucks but yeah
that's actual failure training so he
argues that most people don't really
train to failure because they don't
really fail other researchers aren't so
strict they say well you can judge you
know you can use rpe like rate of
perceived exertion or rir
reps in reserve and you can just judge
like i'm close to failure and you know
there's some research showing that
experienced lifters are pretty decent at
judging when they're gonna fail newbies
don't tend to be but you gain that
expertise over time so the different
types of failure all right let's say in
the research you have to describe a
certain tempo because in the research
you have to spell everything out all
right so the reps were done according to
a two second lowering phase a one second
pause and a one second concentric okay
what that means is two seconds down one
thousand one one thousand two pause 1001
lift 1001 right back into it that's a
four second rep in my experience people
don't really do four second reps that's
just something shown in the research and
written about by certain authors but in
the real world you typically see one
second lowering and one second rising so
a two second rep and some smaller
movements like shrugs and frog pumps you
know it might be three-fourths of a
second per wrap but i have seen you know
deadlift maxes i know the first time i
hit 585 it took me 12 seconds it was a
12 second concentric rep hard to watch
that
so in the research if they say you stuck
to this tempo then technically the set
ends when you can no longer stick to
that tempo well that's hard because you
can't do any breathing reps that way you
know when i do bench press you know
let's say i did 275 for 10 well i would
go
one two three four five six
seven eight
nine
ten rack that's how it's normally done
but if you had a strict tempo
prescription you would have stopped at
six so obviously
that type of failure training according
to a certain tempo is not that taxing
because you really didn't go to failure
which leads me to the next type of
failures failing while allowing for some
rest pause wraps what i just demonstrate
on the bench press were rest pause style
reps right i would at the top i breathe
for a little bit and it allows you to
get a couple more reps that's why
sometimes i prescribe touch and go reps
because on deadlifts if you do touch and
go then you get all the reps done at
once back in the day i train in this
crazy gym called revolution training
systems these badass powerlifters and
you know i remember watching my buddy
mikey uh he was the owner he was doing
deadlifts and he'd be doing a set of
five okay rep one looked like a max rep
two oh my god looked terrible rep three
was like oh my god is he gonna get it
and his nose would start bleeding okay
then he'd be like he'd put the weight
down
and like you know that four and then he
put it down and
then
and he'd be trembling and shaking him
you know his whole body convulsing and
he would get it and that was a fire up
set but it took you know it might have
taken uh uh 60 seconds because of his
breathing at the bottom of the reps well
i would kind of argue that that's rest
pause style training you know did you
get stronger did you set a pr
because you actually got stronger you
know you have more muscle mass or you've
gained coordination or is it because you
just took longer to carry out the set
that's why i tell people like have a cap
you can do rest pause when you do reset
deadlifts you're allowed to have the bar
sitting there but for only three seconds
any more than three seconds and you're
not doing a real set you're doing a rest
pause set you're doing a type of cluster
set so that's something to think about
but the reset reps transfer better to
deadlifting strength in my opinion so
both of them are valuable reset and
touch and go so
both rest pause and touch and go are
both beneficial they both have their
merits and drawbacks but obviously the
rest pause style failure is gonna be
more taxing than the touch and go style
failure now there's another type of
failure where you allow for some cheat
reps okay say i'm doing a set of barbell
curls okay you know say i have 115 on
the bar well i can get probably 15 on my
own you know but i might not stop at 15
i might really use some good english and
really help myself get 16 and 17 up but
then i'm gonna do a strict lowering okay
and really that last rep i'm really
using a lot of momentum but then that
negative is very strict okay so
obviously you know doing no cheating
reps is going to be less taxing than
allowing for some cheat reps now we have
the type of failure where you allow for
form degradation i know that my hip
extensors have always been a lot
stronger than my quads let's say i do a
set of squats okay say i do a set of 10
right maybe my first six reps are you
know at around a 45 degree lean right
which is still kind of upright for me
but then rep seven rep eight rep nine
and then especially rep ten i'm gonna
shoot my hips up and i'm gonna good
morning that thing up you know the tenth
rep does it look more like a squat or a
good morning so what do you do put some
sort of you know you don't know how much
your torso is leaning so the last year
i've really been working on staying more
upright and the set stops when i pass a
certain threshold where my torso leans a
little bit too far but it's hard to
gauge you if you just allow yourself to
keep getting reps regardless of form you
know that's obviously more taxing i'll
give you another example with deadlifts
right you might see someone start out
with an arched back and then as the set
goes on they end up rounding and
rounding if you let them keep grinding
out these rounded back you know some
people are amazing at round back dealers
they'll be fully rounded over and
they'll be you know convulsing and
they'll still get the weight up that's
gonna be way more taxing than stricter
reps so four matters you know the level
of slop that you allow matters with
recovery going to failure with super
strict form is not going to beat you up
compared to using very good textbook
form and stopping the set when you can
no longer do a wrap with textbook form
and finally for my favorite part of this
talk there's the psyched up failure
versus non-psyched failure okay when i
really started pushing the glute squad
you know glue swat san diego you know we
started really motivating each other it
was really kind of a surreal environment
right if you've been following me on
instagram for quite some time then
you'll you'll know what i'm talking
about the camaraderie is through the
roof you know picture having this big
deadlift platform and you've got music
blaring your favorite song you know
everyone had their pr songs downloaded
onto the ipad we'd put on your pr song
you'd be psyched up you would definitely
have an energy drink in you and maybe a
scoop or two of pre-workout in you and
you'd have 15 of your lifting partners
screaming at you come on come on
dominique get this come on go go go lift
left leg and you got 15 people yelling
at the top of their lungs these girls
were setting these crazy feats of
strength you know their deadlift was 3
15 for four and now they hit it for
seven and then the next week they hit it
for ten or something like that you know
my client ashley hodge has hit a 405
pound deadlift on two different
occasions but even more impressive in my
opinion is her 315 for 20 touch and go
reps 315 for 20 and she weighs 130. now
what we realized was we would crush
these crazy pr's and the next five days
we'd be weak you'd be drained with upper
body too and so you realize it wasn't
really fun to have this amazing workout
only to follow it up with like four
workouts in a row of lousy subpar
workouts and in some cases you wouldn't
match that previous level of strength
for like three weeks so we started
realizing like let's save those
psych ups those crazy cheering each
other on situations for the actual
strong lifting meets you know we start
having some of the girls start coming in
in the mornings you know not even
turning the lights on no caffeine no
cyclops no music imagine having it dark
with no music no sound no lifting
partners training alone i remember
watching carly you know training in the
dark calmly hip thrusting you know like
585 pounds for like eight reps or
something with no psychos because she
knew if she can do that under those
circumstances she's definitely gonna
have a big boost during competition i
think pavel satsulin called it training
on the nerve but we learned to not train
on the nerve so much say those crazy
death metal blasting
you know
two scoops of pre-workout
fans cheering you on after you've been
pacing back and forth
envisioning whatever it is that gets you
maximally psyched do that type of
lifting very sporadically you know a few
times a year but it'll tax you a lot
more than training in a non-psyched up
situation now that we've gone over the
types of failure let me finish off with
some practical applications with failure
training not all exercises are created
equal i'm going to discuss two exercises
on the opposite ends of the spectrum
okay on this end you've got deadlifts
all right once you've gotten really good
at deadlifts they're intimidating you
know squats and deadlifts are
intimidating they scare you you might
have trouble sleeping the night before a
hard deadlift session you know what you
have to do and it's very daunting if
you're going for a pr ugh some of my
glute squad girls they get diarrhea the
night before because they're so nervous
because progressive overload gets harder
and harder as you get stronger so when
you do a set of deadlifts to actual
failure it's going to tax you a lot so
say i was doing a set of deadlifts and
you had some sort of like thermal
imaging like
method where you could highlight in red
all the muscles that are being highly
activated okay well much of my body
would be highly active you see my
forearms you'd see the traps all the
back muscles the erectors the lats the
glutes the hammies you know the entire
posterior chain the quads some of the
core muscles everything would be
highlighted in red and the other thing
is they'd be highlighted in red at the
bottom of the movement where your
muscles are all stretched out you're at
long muscle lengths you're stretching
the muscle under heavy load that's
taxing it creates muscle damage it beats
you up it beats up your whole body now
in contrast let's think about a lateral
bandwalk all right when you do a lateral
bandwalk what's going to be highlighted
in red just the upper glutes you know
glute medius loot minimus maybe some tfl
maybe some upper subdivision of the
glute max but it'll just be up in here
all right furthermore you're not working
these muscles in a stretch the hardest
part of lateral bandwalks is when you
reach your leg out and step to the side
at a short muscle lane so it's not going
to create much muscle damage it's not
going to be very taxing on the system
the other thing as i've mentioned in a
previous youtube video when you do
deadlifts you could have someone walk up
to you and aim a gun at you and say i'm
gonna shoot you in the face if you don't
get one more rep and you couldn't get
one more rep like when i deadlifted 650
someone came up to me and said i'm gonna
shoot you in the face i couldn't have
pulled it for a second rep i'm done i'd
lay down and go just kill me now but if
you're doing lateral bend once you stop
this set when you're burning like crazy
okay it gets so uncomfortable a lot of
it's psychological it's this central
governor model you don't like the pain
but you really could get a few more reps
someone had a gun to your head and said
i'm gonna kill you or something with a
reward like hey i'm gonna give you a
million dollars if you somehow get 10
more reps you would get 10 more reps so
oh glad it burns oh
oh
one more one more
oh okay that was failure that was
failure
[__] do ten more who the [__] are you
[__] do ten more right now [__] you
shoot me [__] do 10 more right now
with the high rep band training you're
really not going to true failure you
think you are but you're not so i hope
that illustrates that not all exercises
are created equal can you go to failure
on sub movements yeah rear delt raises
are not going to beat you up much you
don't have to leave a couple reps in the
tank with rear delt raises failure
training is more about the big lifts
your big compound movements that work a
lot of muscle mass you know think of
your squat variations your deadlift
variations leg presses hip thrust
variations chin up variations bench
press variations overhead press
variations weighted dips these are the
exercises that beat you up the most so
that's what we're talking about when we
talk about failure training we're not
talking about curls and tricep
extensions and delt raises so the things
you need to know in order to determine
whether or not you should train the fair
are which exercise which i just went
over what frequency can you do one set
of deadlifts every week to failure yeah
you could probably get away with it
right week in and week out you could do
one set to failure and you could recover
from that and probably utilize
progressive overload interestingly when
i pulled my 650 i was doing one set to
failure each week i don't rely on
deadlifts to build my deadlift i only do
one set per week they beat me up so much
i rely on squats and hip thrusts and
other exercises to build my deadlift but
i have to actually do deadlifts that one
set is vital but i'm not doing much
volume at all now what if you're dead
lifting five times a week can you go to
failure every day no you could no one
could no one could continuously recover
from that for a very long time you'd
quickly overreach you'd spin your wheels
you'd stagnate you wouldn't see any
gains right how about the number of sets
you need to know how many sets you're
doing if you're doing five sets of
squats three times a week that's gonna
be hard to recover from but if you're
doing three sets of squats twice a week
then yeah maybe you can go to failure
and get away with it and even a better
question then how many sets are you
gonna use how many sets to failure are
you gonna do let's say you do four sets
of incline press say you do four sets of
six all right but the fourth set is an
amrap set so set one you get six reps
set two six reps set three six reps set
four maybe you have a little extra
reserve in the tank you might get seven
or eight reps so only the last set was
an actual amrap set that's very
different than taking every set to
failure you know if you did all four
sets to fair that's going to tax you
more than just doing the last set as an
amrap set another question is what else
is in your routine if you're just doing
deadlifts twice a week you know with two
sets you might be able to do
one set per day to fail and get away
with it but what if you're also doing
you know three days of heavy squatting
and two days of barbell bent over rows
you're throwing in some heavy shrugs
maybe some farmer's carries you're doing
a lot of heavy dumbbell work where you
got to pick it up off the ground say
you're doing like leg press or smith
machine hypnosis and you have hundred
pound plates and you're loading those
hundred pound plates or your gym has 150
to 200-pound dumbbells and you're
lugging those things around that taxes
your low back what if you play a sport
or do manual labor what if it's on a
week that you have to move out of your
house or apartment what other things are
you doing that fatigue your low back so
unless you know the answers to all those
questions and more we didn't get into
sleep nutrition stress and you cannot
answer should you train to failure or
not it's a much more nuanced topic than
just saying yes or no so to wrap things
up
should you train a failure the answer is
it depends try to take into
consideration all the things i talked
about in this video as i mentioned in my
rule of thirds video around a third of
your sets can be taken a fair but the
thing is you should have really good
form with those sets and don't allow
sloppy form don't allow cheat reps don't
do rest pause but in my rule of thirds
video on glute training you mix it up a
lot you know you mix up the vectors and
so you're not over taxing any one angle
your lower back doesn't get excessively
beat up the muscles recover and you're
fine research does not support taking
all your sets to failure that's a recipe
for disaster but you also shouldn't fear
failure it's totally fine to go to
failure on many movements especially
single joint exercises just not on all
your sets all right that's a wrap thank
you very much for watching i hope you
enjoyed the video please make sure to
give it a thumbs up make sure you hit
that subscribe button and definitely
leave me a comment if you didn't
understand something i said in the video
you want some clarification i'm happy to
elaborate thanks for watching the video
you